<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Introduction on Axolotz's Med Notes</title><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/</link><description>Recent content in Introduction on Axolotz's Med Notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/1.-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/1.-intro/</guid><description>Overview # A community is a group of people living in the same place or having common characteristics (geography, interests, experiences, concerns, values, etc.).
Community medicine primarily aims to prevent diseases and promote health deals with healthcare issues affecting communities as a whole Physicians, advanced practice nurse, and sometimes physician assistants can provide community medicine services. Community medicine requires a multidisciplinary approach (focuses on different disciplines/specialties)
Core subjects involved in comm.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/2.-primary-health-care/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/2.-primary-health-care/</guid><description>Overview # 3 levels of care: primary, secondary, tertiary
Primary first contact with patient responsible for preventative health care Secondary provides curative healthcare facilities patients with abnormalities are referred to secondary Tertiary provides more advanced curative healthcare facilities for specialized healthcare or when there are not enough facilities PHC initially gained gained global prominence in the 1978 Alma Ata Declaration in the Soviet Union.
The Alma Ata Declaration states:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/1.-inflammation-overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/1.-inflammation-overview/</guid><description>Inflammation Overview # Vascularized tissue response to injury (e.g: infection or tissue damage) Cells/molecules are recruited from circulation and moved to site to eliminate offending agent. Inflammation is protective in nature. Cardinal Signs # Infl. has 5 major cardinal signs (cardinal sign = major signs/symptoms)
Redness Swelling Heat Pain Loss of function e.g: cannot use toe with grout can be remembered with the song: Red, Swelling, Heat and Pain (heat and pain)!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/2.-acute-inflammation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/2.-acute-inflammation/</guid><description>Acute Inflammation Overview # Acute inflammation lasts minutes to days. It is characterized by exudation of fluid and plasma protein and emigration of leukocytes (predominantly neotrophils).
Acute inflammations have 2 major components:
Vascular changes (vasodilation, increased vascular permeability, etc.) Cellular changes (leukocyte migration then elimination of injurious agent) Previously we have talked about R1 (recognition). These notes talk about R2 (recruitment) and R3 (removal). Vascular and cellular changes discussed here are within R2 and R3.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/3.-mediators/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/3.-mediators/</guid><description>Overview # To avoid tissue injury, the inflammatory response needs to be controlled and regulated.
There are mechanisms in place to control, regulate, and eventually terminate the inflammatory response:
mediators are produced in rapid bursts (not continous) release is stimulus dependent short half-lives degrade after release neutrophil/PMN short life production of stop signals at the end of IR there are neural inhibitors There are major general features of mediators of inflammation:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/4.-morphology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/4.-morphology/</guid><description>Overview # Morphology is the outward appearance of something (i.e: shape, structure, colour, pattern, size).
The vascular and cellular reactions that characterize acute inflammation are reflected in the morphologic appearance of the reaction.
The main causes are vascular dilation and accumulation of WBCs in extracellular space.
characteristic latin name redness rubor warmth calor swelling tumor loss of function functio laese pain dolor most gross or microscopic morphological features are usually caused by R1 &amp;amp; R2</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/5.-chronic-inflammation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/5.-chronic-inflammation/</guid><description>Outcomes of Acute Inflammation # An acute inflammation typicalls takes one of three major outcomes:
Complete Resolution Healing by Fibrosis Chronic Inflammation limited injury, minimal tissue destruction substantial tissue destruction, causing scar. May or may not impede function. acute cannot resolve, injurious agent persists, inflammation progresses into chronic. Complete resolution is the desirable outcome.
Chronic Inflammation Overview # Prolonged inflammation (weeks, months, maybe years) Inflammation, tissue injury, and repair attempts occur simultaneously eventually causing scarring, impacting organ function Chronic usually follows acute, but not always the case.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/6.-repair/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/6.-repair/</guid><description> Overview #</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/9.-mid-question-bank/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/9.-mid-question-bank/</guid><description>Inflammation # Acute inflammation characteristically involves:
A) Constriction of arterioles B) Capillary endothelial cell enlargement C) Influx of macrophages D) Influx of mast cells E) Influx of neutrophils answer ... E) Influx of neutrophils Which of the following is true regarding toll like receptors?
A) They circulate in the blood B) Collectins are examples of TLRs C) They are essential for chemotaxis D) They recognize PAMPs answer ... D) They recognize PAMPs A 36-year-old man has had midepigastric abdominal pain for the past 3 months.</description></item></channel></rss>