<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Introduction on Axolotz's Med Notes</title><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/</link><description>Recent content in Introduction on Axolotz's Med Notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/1.-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/1.-intro/</guid><description>Overview # A community is a group of people living in the same place or having common characteristics (geography, interests, experiences, concerns, values, etc.).
Community medicine primarily aims to prevent diseases and promote health deals with healthcare issues affecting communities as a whole Physicians, advanced practice nurse, and sometimes physician assistants can provide community medicine services. Community medicine requires a multidisciplinary approach (focuses on different disciplines/specialties)
Core subjects involved in comm.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/2.-primary-health-care/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/community-medicine/2.-primary-health-care/</guid><description>Overview # 3 levels of care: primary, secondary, tertiary
Primary first contact with patient responsible for preventative health care Secondary provides curative healthcare facilities patients with abnormalities are referred to secondary Tertiary provides more advanced curative healthcare facilities for specialized healthcare or when there are not enough facilities PHC initially gained gained global prominence in the 1978 Alma Ata Declaration in the Soviet Union.
The Alma Ata Declaration states:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/2.-cellular-respiration-overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/2.-cellular-respiration-overview/</guid><description>Overview # ATP is the &amp;ldquo;energy currency&amp;rdquo; of the cell. It is the &amp;ldquo;energy molecule&amp;rdquo; of almost all forms of life, and is used to power many energy-requiring cellular reactions.
Cellular respiration is a metabolic pathway that breaks down glucose to yield ATP (i.e: glucose from your food is broken down to yield ATP for energy)
During this process, glucose and oxygen are converted into carbon dioxide and water.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/3.-glycolysis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/3.-glycolysis/</guid><description>Overview # Glycolysis is a metabolic pathway, meaning that the product of one rxn is the substrate of the next. Glycolysis does not require oxygen.
It is the breaking down of glucose to pyruvate (thus the name glyco-lysis) It is a universal pathway found in all cell types Generates ATP Does not require oxygen Anabolic pathway (constructs molecules from smaller units) Glycolysis is made up of 2 &amp;ldquo;phases&amp;rdquo;. An &amp;ldquo;energy-requiring&amp;rdquo; phase that uses ATP, and an &amp;ldquo;energy-releasing&amp;rdquo; phase that generates ATP.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/4.-pyruvate-use/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/4.-pyruvate-use/</guid><description>Overview # Glycolysis produced pyruvate molecules. That pyruvate can now be used up via a number of different pathways.
If there is oxygen, pyruvate goes through aerobic respiration (oxygen-requiring) to yield even more ATP.
If there is a lack of oxygen it will go through anaerobic pathways (non-oxygen requiring), where glycolysis is repeated over and over to become the major source for ATP.
There are 4 major pathways that pyruvate could go through:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/5.-glycogen-metabolism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/5.-glycogen-metabolism/</guid><description>Structure and Function # Glycogen is the stored form of glucose that is made up of many connected glucose molecules. A single glycogen molecule consists of hundreds of thousands of glucose molecules.
glycogen Glycogen can be synthesized and degraded. There is about 400g of glycogen in muscle, 100g in liver. They function to:
Muscle glycogen serves as fuel reserve for ATP synthesis during muscle contraction Liver glycogen is to maintain blood glucose concentration (particularly during the early stages of a fast) When degraded, glucose is released as glucose-1-P, which has to be isomerized (into glucose-6-P) first before going into glycolysis.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/6.-mid-question-bank/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/6.-mid-question-bank/</guid><description>After digestion of a piece of cake that contains four, milk, and sucrose as its primary ingredients, the major carbohydrate products entering the blood are which one of the following? Choose the best answer.
A) Glucose B) Fructose and galactose C) Galactose and glucose D) Fructose and glucose E) Glucose, fructose, galactose answer ... E) Glucose, fructose, galactose Which one of the following transporters increases its uptake of glucose in response to insulin?</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/1.-inflammation-overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/1.-inflammation-overview/</guid><description>Inflammation Overview # Vascularized tissue response to injury (e.g: infection or tissue damage) Cells/molecules are recruited from circulation and moved to site to eliminate offending agent. Inflammation is protective in nature. Cardinal Signs # Infl. has 5 major cardinal signs (cardinal sign = major signs/symptoms)
Redness Swelling Heat Pain Loss of function e.g: cannot use toe with grout can be remembered with the song: Red, Swelling, Heat and Pain (heat and pain)!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/2.-acute-inflammation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/2.-acute-inflammation/</guid><description>Acute Inflammation Overview # Acute inflammation lasts minutes to days. It is characterized by exudation of fluid and plasma protein and emigration of leukocytes (predominantly neotrophils).
Acute inflammations have 2 major components:
Vascular changes (vasodilation, increased vascular permeability, etc.) Cellular changes (leukocyte migration then elimination of injurious agent) Previously we have talked about R1 (recognition). These notes talk about R2 (recruitment) and R3 (removal). Vascular and cellular changes discussed here are within R2 and R3.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/3.-mediators/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/3.-mediators/</guid><description>Overview # To avoid tissue injury, the inflammatory response needs to be controlled and regulated.
There are mechanisms in place to control, regulate, and eventually terminate the inflammatory response:
mediators are produced in rapid bursts (not continous) release is stimulus dependent short half-lives degrade after release neutrophil/PMN short life production of stop signals at the end of IR there are neural inhibitors There are major general features of mediators of inflammation:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/4.-morphology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/4.-morphology/</guid><description>Overview # Morphology is the outward appearance of something (i.e: shape, structure, colour, pattern, size).
The vascular and cellular reactions that characterize acute inflammation are reflected in the morphologic appearance of the reaction.
The main causes are vascular dilation and accumulation of WBCs in extracellular space.
characteristic latin name redness rubor warmth calor swelling tumor loss of function functio laese pain dolor most gross or microscopic morphological features are usually caused by R1 &amp;amp; R2</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/5.-chronic-inflammation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/5.-chronic-inflammation/</guid><description>Outcomes of Acute Inflammation # An acute inflammation typicalls takes one of three major outcomes:
Complete Resolution Healing by Fibrosis Chronic Inflammation limited injury, minimal tissue destruction substantial tissue destruction, causing scar. May or may not impede function. acute cannot resolve, injurious agent persists, inflammation progresses into chronic. Complete resolution is the desirable outcome.
Chronic Inflammation Overview # Prolonged inflammation (weeks, months, maybe years) Inflammation, tissue injury, and repair attempts occur simultaneously eventually causing scarring, impacting organ function Chronic usually follows acute, but not always the case.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/6.-repair/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/6.-repair/</guid><description>Overview # Tissue repair is part of the inflammatory response&amp;rsquo;s (5th &amp;ldquo;R&amp;rdquo;).
Inflammation may cause injury, repair is critical after eliminating injurious agent.
Repair can be achieved by two types of rxns:
Regeneration (1st intention repair) occurs in mild and superficial injuries. replaces damaged components and essentially returns to pre-injury state. Scar and Fibrosis (2nd intention repair) occurs in severe injury repair occurs by laying down connective (fibrous) tissue Both require mediators, cellular proliferation, and interactions within the ECM.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/7.-mid-question-bank/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pathology/7.-mid-question-bank/</guid><description>Inflammation # Acute inflammation characteristically involves:
A) Constriction of arterioles B) Capillary endothelial cell enlargement C) Influx of macrophages D) Influx of mast cells E) Influx of neutrophils answer ... E) Influx of neutrophils Which of the following is true regarding toll like receptors?
A) They circulate in the blood B) Collectins are examples of TLRs C) They are essential for chemotaxis D) They recognize PAMPs answer ... D) They recognize PAMPs A 36-year-old man has had midepigastric abdominal pain for the past 3 months.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/1.-pharmacokinetics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/1.-pharmacokinetics/</guid><description>Overview # Pharmokinetics is the effect of the body on drugs (i.e: what the body does to the drug).
Pharmacokinetics is the study of drug absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion (ADME).
Goal is to reach a desired beneficial effect with minimal adverse effects possible. clinician must determine the dose that most closely achieves this There is a relationship between the drug&amp;rsquo;s effect and its concentration at the active site General rule: any adverse effects that can be prevented should be prevented.</description></item></channel></rss>