<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Axolotz's Med Notes</title><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/</link><description>Recent content on Axolotz's Med Notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/2.-cellular-respiration-overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/2.-cellular-respiration-overview/</guid><description>Overview # ATP is the &amp;ldquo;energy currency&amp;rdquo; of the cell. It is the &amp;ldquo;energy molecule&amp;rdquo; of almost all forms of life, and is used to power many energy-requiring cellular reactions.
Cellular respiration is a metabolic pathway that breaks down glucose to yield ATP (i.e: glucose from your food is broken down to yield ATP for energy)
During this process, glucose and oxygen are converted into carbon dioxide and water.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/3.-glycolysis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/3.-glycolysis/</guid><description>Overview # Glycolysis is a metabolic pathway, meaning that the product of one rxn is the substrate of the next. Glycolysis does not require oxygen.
It is the breaking down of glucose to pyruvate (thus the name glyco-lysis) It is a universal pathway found in all cell types Generates ATP Does not require oxygen Anabolic pathway (constructs molecules from smaller units) Glycolysis is made up of 2 &amp;ldquo;phases&amp;rdquo;. An &amp;ldquo;energy-requiring&amp;rdquo; phase that uses ATP, and an &amp;ldquo;energy-releasing&amp;rdquo; phase that generates ATP.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/4.-pyruvate-use/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/4.-pyruvate-use/</guid><description>Overview # Glycolysis produced pyruvate molecules. That pyruvate can now be used up via a number of different pathways.
If there is oxygen, pyruvate goes through aerobic respiration (oxygen-requiring) to yield even more ATP.
If there is a lack of oxygen it will go through anaerobic pathways (non-oxygen requiring), where glycolysis is repeated over and over to become the major source for ATP.
There are 4 major pathways that pyruvate could go through:</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/5.-glycogen-metabolism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/5.-glycogen-metabolism/</guid><description>Structure and Function # Glycogen is the stored form of glucose that is made up of many connected glucose molecules. A single glycogen molecule consists of hundreds of thousands of glucose molecules.
glycogen Glycogen can be synthesized and degraded. There is about 400g of glycogen in muscle, 100g in liver. They function to:
Muscle glycogen serves as fuel reserve for ATP synthesis during muscle contraction Liver glycogen is to maintain blood glucose concentration (particularly during the early stages of a fast) When degraded, glucose is released as glucose-1-P, which has to be isomerized (into glucose-6-P) first before going into glycolysis.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/6.-mid-question-bank/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/metabolism/6.-mid-question-bank/</guid><description>After digestion of a piece of cake that contains four, milk, and sucrose as its primary ingredients, the major carbohydrate products entering the blood are which one of the following? Choose the best answer.
A) Glucose B) Fructose and galactose C) Galactose and glucose D) Fructose and glucose E) Glucose, fructose, galactose answer ... E) Glucose, fructose, galactose Which one of the following transporters increases its uptake of glucose in response to insulin?</description></item></channel></rss>