<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Axolotz's Med Notes</title><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/</link><description>Recent content on Axolotz's Med Notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/1.-pharmacokinetics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/1.-pharmacokinetics/</guid><description>Overview # Pharmacokinetics is the effect of the body on drugs (i.e: what the body does to the drug).
Pharmacokinetics is the study of drug absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion (ADME).
Goal is to reach a desired beneficial effect with minimal adverse effects possible. clinician must determine the dose that most closely achieves this There is a relationship between the drug&amp;rsquo;s effect and its concentration at the active site General rule: any adverse effects that can be prevented should be prevented.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/2.-pharmacodynamics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/2.-pharmacodynamics/</guid><description>Overview # Pharmacodynamics is the effect of the drugs on the body (biochemical and physiological).
Most drugs exert their effect by interacting with specialized target macromolecules called receptors. Binding with receptor will cause conformational changes or a biochemical effect.
Receptors determine specificity of drug Most are proteins Most drugs bind reversibly (non-covelant) Not all drugs use receptors Two fundamental properties underly specificity in drug-receptor interactions:
Complementarity of shape between drug and receptor (lock and key model) complementarity in electrostatic, hydrophobic, and hydrogen bonding surfaces of each component lock and key model Recognition sites are molecular regions of the receptor to which ligands bind to</description></item><item><title/><link>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/3.-routes-of-administration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://axolotz.github.io/mednotes/docs/notes/y2/s1/pharmacology/3.-routes-of-administration/</guid><description>Overview # 3 major routes:
Enternal: via GI tract Paternal: non-intestinal means of administration Other Enteral Routes # Oral (PO) # Drug should be swallowed Most commonly used route Safest, most convenient, most economical Duodenum is the major site of absorption, but stomach, jejunum and ileum may be involved Disadvantages: patient must be cooperative (compliant) absorption is variable due to several factors vomiting failure of disintegration and dissolution first-pass effect drug may be destroyed by gastric acid or intestinal flora food may delay absorption alteration in intestinal motility may affect absorption absorption may be affected by splanchnic blood flow Sublingual (SL) # Drug is placed under tongue Avoids first-pass effect Used when a rapid onset is required (such as in angina pectoris) Not commonly used Rectal (PR) # Avoids first-pass effect partially (~ 50%) Useful in unconscious or vomiting patients Absorption is often irregular, incomplete, and unpredictable Can be used for a local effect Used for drugs poorly absorbed from, or unstable in the GIT Used for rapid effect Aseptic technique is required Paternal Routes # Intravenous (IV) # Bolus vs infusion Only aqueous solutions may be injected IV Rapid onset of action Oily vehicles or those that precipitate blood constituents should NOT be given IV No first-pass hepatic metabolism drug goes first to right side of the heart, lung, left side of heart, then to systemic circulation Disadvantages: produce high initial concentration of the drug that might be toxic Intramuscular (IM) # Drug is injected within muscle fibers of deltoid, gluteus maximus or vastus lateralis Absorption of drug depends on blood supply (slower for g.</description></item></channel></rss>